The overall environment in which I operate is
the engine that can help me grow.
If I take a seed and put it in the fridge, not much will happen.
If I place it in the soil, with light, sun, and warmth, it can thrive.
If you're in a complicated emotional environment or otherwise, it will
influence you.
We increasingly know we can refer to the genetic egg and more and more, we talk about epigenetics.
The power of the environment accounts for almost 90% of
this strength.
We must consider what environment your patient lives in.
I often ask the question, where do you live, what are you experiencing,
what have you been through, what are...
This is all part of the anamnesis, but in the idea of, I take a layer
around and observe.
What is happening. We need an environment to grow
and secondly
space. Giving mental space, giving space to tissue,
and giving space
to an emotion. Embryology is functional anatomy. And
what does that mean? It means
that anatomy is primarily in motion. Secondly, c
anatomy uses
the four years.
five dimensions we know, up, down, left, etc. And the fourth dimension
is the concept of chronos, of time. You will need to look at this
small developing embryo through all its movements and also with cross-sections. This
concept relates to memory. This notion of time also involves memory,
meaning you carry time within you. You are a concentration
of time. And
sometimes there are specific areas in the body.
These are concentrated areas where a person is stuck.
A word, a gesture, a look can block a person for life.
And sometimes, that time manifests in the tissues.
And sometimes you can work, you may have noticed,
you did some work, and then suddenly,
an emotional release occurs.
You have released, in fact, a concentration.
You place it back in its space.
And this is important in embryology.
Because we can reconnect these concepts.
If you remember the short film we watched this morning,
you saw movements where we moved forward,
and then suddenly, movements that went backward.
Movements as if there were waves, like that.
But if you observe that, if there is a movement like that,
it indicates support points.
And we will use them as points of therapeutic tools.
Because the body knows these support points.
If you provide good support,
it knows where it can develop, it can rebuild.
There is the notion that you have time, that there are tissues, that there are fluids,
and all this expresses itself in a constellation,
saying that mind, body, spirit are united.
Mind, body, spirit.
So osteopathy is a science based on the art of touch,
which offers real knowledge of the living body,
that tells the story of anatomy,
related to the movement of spirit and mind.
One of the goals of osteopathy is to enhance exchanges
and to have an impact even at the cellular level,
and even, I think we go further,
that we can have impacts down to the genetic level.
We now prove this through the phenomena of tensegrity
and epigenetic phenomena,
which actually show us that we have a deep impact,
and we will see how far it goes.
The path...
My professor, whom my teacher suggested, told me that first you need to study embryology.
He said that when you really understand embryology, you will understand what anatomy means.
Anatomy will give you physiology.
This physiology, you will also need to study its pathos.
Its pathophysiology.
Then we have psychology, then we have philosophy.
Finally, there is spirituality.
How conception develops, and where it is how I die.
That death...
on a developmental level
is useful.
If there is no cellular death,
I don't like the word death,
I always prefer transformation.
It's a continuous transformation.
This power that was already established
at the first cell,
continues until the end of your life.
Up until your last breath.
That is to say you have this ability
to take in the breath of life.
The breath of life is there
and then I release my breath
and I still have
the energy to
take in more
so I can participate again
and we do this repeatedly; that's where transformation occurs
I think sometimes people
are stuck in time
and they come sometimes to seek
information about it
There are often people who follow
these courses, and then in practice,
something happens
because
we enter a space where the mind cannot intervene,
but there is a modification occurring inside.
Because we will witness the development of the perfect embryo, as we say.
We will be in the blueprint, which maintains its midline, which has no deviation.
That is my birth; it's the space of my conception.
And sometimes you have the midline here; you are in the right axis.
Sometimes you may already deviate at conception.
You can be deviated at birth; you may deviate due to trauma.
And you must recognize
these points.
The lack of recognition
creates all
compensatory activities.
So at some point,
through the quality of my presence,
through the quality of touch,
as the tissue informs you,
you can recognize
these spaces.
And then there can be
a...
a trust
for correction
you just need to be present
to touch
because there isn't the will
that's really important
the body has a self-regulating capacity
self-regulation
and can maintain its health
and thus this notion of strength
from nature
is about reconnecting with that
we can see very clearly
if now there is no longer human impact
nature quickly reclaims its rights and we have somewhat been cut off from
that. In this development, nature is present. The less we intervene, the better it
is. Another
principle is the notion of reciprocity of structure and function and
the entirety of
these principles indicates that the body must consider all of this and
thus be aware
that I can utilize this.
It is truly practical.
That it has this power.
And what does it ask for?
It simply needs to be adjusted.
There are doctors who specialize in little fingers.
That's fantastic.
At the same time, they don't see that the lower limb, for example, or the upper limb,
is an expansion of a peritoneal sac.
Atoms will form molecules.
Molecules will form cells.
Cells form tissues.
Tissues form organs.
So, ultimately, I am a kind of package
of atoms in front of you that moves.
And before the atom, there is also this whole notion of energy.
So ultimately, what we perceive is a bundle of energy.
It's an energy package that sometimes needs a bit of structuring.
That thinks, too.
Onto, Genesis.
Onto means being.
And Genesis means formation.
Ontogeny is the formation of a being.
We will study human ontogeny.
And especially in its morphogenetics.
So in its morpho, in its shape, and
the formation of that shape.
An individual.
Phylogeny takes back the history of the development of all species.
over time. We will study human ontogeny. We will mainly
explore the shape
and the power of the development of the human being and see the impacts we can have
at the level of practice.